Maxine Seelbinder Merlino
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Maxine Seelbinder Merlino papers
1928-2003
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Merlino, Maxine Ollie Seelbinder
1.1 linear feet
The papers of illustrator, muralist, theatrical set designer, and professor Maxine Seelbinder Merlino papers measure 1.1 linear feet and date from 1928-2003. The collection includes correspondence; newspaper clippings and reviews of artist's work; sketches for stage and set designs and mural decorations; federal commission contracts; exhibition brochures; theater playbills and announcements; photographs; original art work, including drawings and sketches; original lithographs; and material on the dedication of the Merlino Gallery at California State University, Long Beach.
Biographical Note
Maxine Ollie Seelbinder Merlino was born in Portland, Oregon in 1912. She trained at the Portland Art Museum School before venturing to New York City where she took classes at the Art Students' League with, among others, Will Barnet, Anton Refregier, Adolph Gottlieb, Hans Hofmann, and Harry Sternberg. Maxine Merlino worked in New York from 1936 to 1943 as a free-lance illustrator, muralist, and theatrical set designer.
In 1940 and 1942, Merlino won mural commissions for the United States Department of Interior Section of Fine Arts program. She designed and executed murals for the S.S. Garfield, and painted a mural that graced the Recorder of Deeds Building in Washington, D.C., one of seven murals in the building celebrating the contributions of African Americans.
Relocating to Long Beach, California in 1943, she worked as a scientific illustrator for the Army Air Force during the Second World War and subsequently as a stage, set and costume designer for theater and film producer Preston Sturges. From the early 1950s until her retirement in 1976, she was affiliated with California State University, Long Beach where she served as a Professor of Art and Theater Design and then as Dean of the Art Department. In recognition of Dr. Merlino's contributions to the department, the university dedicated an art gallery in her name, in February 2003.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of illustrator, muralist, theatrical set designer, and professor, Maxine Seelbinder Merlino papers measures 1.1 linear feet and date from 1928-2003. The collection includes correspondence; newspaper clippings and reviews of artist's work; sketches for stage and set designs and mural decorations; federal commission contracts; exhibition brochures; theater playbills and announcements; photographs; original art work, including watercolor sketches; original lithographs; and material on the dedication of the Merlino Gallery at California State University, Long Beach.
Documenting Merlino's work on New Deal federal government programs are letters sent to her in the early 1940s from the Public Buildings Administration and the Section of Fine Arts of the Federal Works Agency in Washington, D.C. as well as three photographs of a mural executed by Merlino for the Recorder of Deeds Building in Washington, D.C. that depicts Benjamin Banneker, a pioneering African-American surveyor, inventor, and astronomer.
Representing Merlino's early New York period are brochures of group exhibitions and her one-woman show in a theater gallery. Among the original works of art are two original lithographs: Franco's Destruction, which was reproduced in a 1938 issue of New Masses, and Hearst's Empire, which appeared in the April 1938 edition of The Fight magazine.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as five series:
Series 1: Biographical, 1929-2003 (Box 1; 5 folders)
Series 2: Letters, 1936-2001 (Box 1; 6 folders)
Series 3: Projects, 1927-2002 (Box 1-2; 26 folders)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1939-1969 (Box 1-2; 13 folders)
Series 5: Works of Art, 1932-1957 (Box 1, 3, OV 4; 21 folders)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms.
Subjects:
California State University, Long Beach -- Faculty
Subjects-Topical:
Art -- Study and teaching; Set designers -- California; Mural painting and decoration -- 20th century -- California; Federal aid to the arts
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Works of art; Drawings
Provenance
Dr. Merlino donated her papers in 2003.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical, 1929-2003, Series 1:; (Box 1; 5 folders)
  - Résumés, 1949-1962 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clipping, 1929-2003, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Certificates and Awards, 1932-1999 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
- Letters, 1936-2001, Series 2:; (Box 1; 6 folders)
  - Art Student's League, 1936-1940 (Box 1)
  - The Fight magazine, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Harry Sternberg, 1939 (Box 1)
  - National Art Society, New York World's Fair, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Federal Works Agency, 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - California State University, Long Beach, 1952-2001 (Box 1)
- Projects, 1937-2002, Series 3:; (Box 1-2, 26 folders)
  - S.S. Garfield, U.S. Maritime Commission (see also Box 2), 1940-1941, (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Playbills, Westchester Drama Association, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, Westchester Drama Association, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Recorder of Deeds Building mural, Washington, D.C., 1943-2002, (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - Photocopies of mural submissions, 1939-1941 (Box 1)
  - Snapshots of various mural designs, 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, mural designs for Colonial Restaurant, 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Photocopies, Drawing Depot technical illustrations, 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, US Air Corps murals for Officer's Club, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Preston Sturges, The Players Theatre and Restaurant (see also Box 2), undated, 1951-1998, (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - Photographs, Set designs, 1951-1953 (Box 1)
  - Mural designs, Seafood restaurant in Seal Beach (photocopies), undated (Box 1)
  - Mural designs, restaurant in Long Beach (photocopies), undated (Box 1)
  - Oversized Project Files, 1937-2002, (5 folders) (Box 2 (sol))
- Printed Material, 1939-1969, Series 4:; (Box 1-2, 13 folders)
  - Exhibition catalogs, 1930s-1941 (Box 1)
  - Exhibition catalog and letters, Art Institute of Chicago, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Magazine, The Art Digest, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1936-1969, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Academy of Ballet and Theatre Arts, 1957-1958, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Oversized Magazine articles featuring Merlino illustrations, 1930s-1969, (5 folders) (Box 2 (sol))
- Works of Art, 1932-1957, Series 5:; (Box 1, 3, OV 4; 21 folders)
  - Drawings, undated-1932 (Box 1)
  - Sketches, The 49er, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Prints, The New Yorker, undated (Box 1)
  - Oversized Illustrations with Magazines, 1937-1957, (8 folders) (Box 3 (sol))
  - Oversized Lithographs, undated, (8 folders) (Box 3 (sol))
  - Oversized Gouache and 2 Charcoal Drawings, 1936-1943 (Box 3 (sol))
  - Oversized Lithograph, Munitions Magnet, c. 1938 (Box OV 4)